hello bante
my name is jiga and i think
we can start with the with the subject
of fear i think we can all agree that
most of our everyday actions
are in some way based in different
ways of different
kinds of fears i often
go to the to the root cause to the
origins of
every fear and i think this is my
subject view that there should be
one uh one fundamental root cause of
all fears we experience every day so my
question is what is this in your
view what is this the root cause
of those fears and how can we
tackle it well the root cause is death
fear of death
and dying every fear coming it's that's
that's what every fear is rooted you
know fear of losing possessions
losing loved ones not getting what you
want it's all
fearful because it implies certain
end of your life or at least end of your
life the way you know it
so you can't tackle it in a sense of to
not have it
because for as long as you're alive
you're liable to death
and that's why the ultimate
contemplation the buddha was talking
about of
of maranusati so you can't you can't get
rid of it the only thing you can do
is develop your mind in regard to it
through samadhi through sila samadhi and
then through understanding
but in order to do that uh you pretty
much need to stop ignoring the fact
that um you're gonna die
so when people act in their life towards
things families ambitions every single of those
families ambitions every single of those
actions
is underlined by the
their mind ignoring their own mortality
they never think that
i might not even live to see the end of
this because other because the life will
because other because the life will
become quite unpleasant
and that's that's uh that's an
inevitable step unless you admit
the unpleasantness of life condemned to
death you cannot develop your mind
towards death correctly the way the word
was teaching
so the first step is to develop very
strict virtue
sense restraint and keep the precepts
because otherwise the mind probably will
not be able to bear it
if that's the direction you want to go
and contemplate
okay thank you uh then another
question it's from raymond how to calm
the mind
especially when are in distress and we
fail to
cut the flow of thought even observing
breathing does not help
i would be happy for practical solution
uh you calm your mind when you're
distressed by calming your mind before you get
by calming your mind before you get
distressed so don't wait till you're
distressed to start calming your mind
the only reason your mind is not calm
when you're distressed is because you
haven't cultivate calmness when you were
not distressed
so before distress comes your way and it
will one way or the other
uh start restraining and not
acting out of pressures towards pleasure
towards avoiding pain endure that
and that's already preparing you for
when the stress or any other stress
comes you will already have a ground for not
you will already have a ground for not
resisting it blindly and spinning out of
control
so there is absolutely no samadhi no
calmness without the basis of virtue and precepts
without the basis of virtue and precepts
it's absolutely not negotiable
so if a person doesn't doesn't keep
precepts or not so strictly or not
really committed to them or sometimes
yes sometimes no
well that's the type of somatic you will
have sometimes you'll you'll you'll avoid
sometimes you'll you'll you'll avoid
this stress sometimes you want but
either way you will be subjected to it
best way of dealing with the stress when
it happens so suppose we were not
following your advice
right right so you haven't followed the
advice and now this distress happens and
you will follow it in the future but how
to deal with the stress that has
happened endure it there is no magical
endure it there is no magical
magical fix basically uh
if mind is not strong the endurance will
be unpleasant if mind is strong
the endurance can be pleasant it doesn't
matter what it is
that's like in the suttas when the
buddha would be abused by people
uh shouted insults at him or something
and then some people noticed
look the the target he's getting even
brighter and happier when people do that
to him because he just reminds him how
free he is
um so if if person is not developed and
the stress is there
make sure you don't do anything on
account of that distress
that then later you have to deal with so
endure it and even if it's like the
advice from the suttas if you
greet grit your teeth uh press the
tongue at the top against the top of the the
at the top against the top of the the
roof of your mouth and endure it until
it passes
and then don't be careless when it
disappears don't forget that
it will come back
it's not going to last forever that's
for sure it doesn't matter how bad it is
the mind cannot possibly it the mind
itself will run out of energy to
just to spin out of control so you have
to wait till that happens
and then start practicing and not be
careless again
is this also part of the practice
enduring it and not getting distracted
absolutely yeah but that is the core of
the practice
the as they would have said enduring
patiently is the only
it's the foremost and the only type of
austerity you know endurance
that he approves of it's it's it's the
austerity that can result actually in in
that can result actually in in
liberation so
people can endure all sorts of things
people can endure
dying out of hunger people can endure
not breathing and whatever else
those ascetics we're doing to
self-torture but people what they cannot endue is
but people what they cannot endue is
distress and fear on the mental level
without acting out of it
for that you need wisdom and if you do
it you will get wisdom
so it was the suta i don't remember the
exact number but it was basically when
this man was talking about types of
austerity which one that the target
approves of
and he said he done or he did all of
them he went through it
at one point he stopped breeding and had
all this like he said basically if there
are physical pains to be experienced on
a
of enduring he has experienced them and
none of that
was the right way and not acting out of
uh out of craving towards your own
feelings and he said a person who can
endure that
that is the foremost austerity nothing
else can match that
even if somebody you know i don't know
hangs from top of a tree never eats and
never drinks water and dies like that or
something that's not even close and the reason why
that's not even close and the reason why
people do these extreme austerities by
the way
and and endurance says is because they
can't endure their own feelings without
acting out of them
so it's easier to double down and jump
into it and try to deal with it on your
own terms
and that's what ignorance is you're not
in control
and you need to start admitting that and
feeling the weight of it
so a related question how to practice
sensory restraint in the presence of
stimuli uh
does not depend on your will understand
the restraint of the senses
in the sense that say you don't eat or
listen to music because of the
pleasure what about when you weren't
looking for a pleasant
solution but you still find yourself in
it
say do you you eat at the restaurant
when there is a good music
when you drive past a very beautiful
view when someone hugs you
i know that by uh retreating into
solitude can minimize how often this happens but
can minimize how often this happens but
it seems to me
that this may fall more into run of
monastic life
uh when when you are in the world the
exposure to some of these things is
inevitable so what you do is you have to realize
so what you do is you have to realize
that
well it's already a compromise
so you can't expect to to for your mind
to develop as much as you would if you
learn how to deal with solitude
and if you're fine with that compromise
then just
make sure to be very careful when you
are in control of your circumstances so when
in control of your circumstances so when
you do have a say
make sure you don't slip up and then if
accident you know if somebody hugs you
or something well
it won't last for three hours it's going
to be 10 seconds
and that's fine so you can endure it
because your mind has been sufficiently
withdrawn from it when you were in
charge of making these choices
so in other words if when you are in
charge of your sense restraint
if you if if you invest effort proper
effort sufficient effort there
you won't worry as much about all these
kind of accidental exposures because
the mind will not immediately leap up
onto them
because it has already created some
buffer zone through the sensory strain
that you practice beforehand
okay hello my name is sebastian
um i have a question uh
about um concrete suggestions
for a lay follower though so for someone
who has decided
for some reason let's just assume at
this point that this is uh
the fact of the matter that that person
cannot ordain at that particular point
so what would be some concrete
suggestions say
um taking into account the vicissitudes
of contemporary life
as to how one could cultivate the
virtuous and contemplative life
as wisely and efficiently as possible
for instance how to engage
with sexual restraint with limited food
consumption solitude having contact with like-minded
solitude having contact with like-minded
people and so on and so forth
so what would be say some of your
concrete suggestions
for someone in a lay setting
how could that person pursue these
activities and disciplines
as efficiently as possible given the
circumstances some person can adjust it this way some
some person can adjust it this way some
person can address the other way
the point is the adjustment whatever
that might be
should be about uh minimizing your
exposure to things that will tempt you
and pressure you
where there is a good likelihood you
will give in
so just sell your tv
minimize your internet only use it as a
tool when you need it
no browsing of the news movies series
read use it for suitors and studies
minimize if like unless you have to go
to work where there are other people
then when you don't have to go to work
don't go and socialize just for the sake
of distraction
so basically just uh read about the five
precepts or eight precepts
and see what you can do to support what
those precepts require
and then see where you fail and then
improve there
so you have to as i said in the um in my
response to the earlier
question you have to recognize it is
already a compromise situation
but uh so you will have to do more of
like a
side work uh aimed
aimed at the managing the circumstances
because they will tend to impress you
i would have a an additional question
here it's a very practical one and one that i
it's a very practical one and one that i
was curious about for quite some time in
certain christian traditions for
instance you would hate
you would have laid movements that would
um imitate to a certain degree
a monastic lifestyle so this is
something that has emerged
in specific times throughout the history
where lay people had this feeling or
desire to um to engage into
to um to engage into
a in a lifestyle that that would be
similar uh to to the monastic lifestyle i was
uh to to the monastic lifestyle i was
just curious whether in the tiravada
tradition there is something of the kind whether
there is something of the kind whether
there is a say
an institution of sorts um
that is meant for lay people
who would be interested in pursuing say
the path of wisdom
more intensively without necessarily
uh undergoing the full ordination
yeah well i think that's that's what the
buddha encouraged to people
back in the day that didn't that
couldn't ordain or that um
disrobed out of weakness or whatever
else to to at least go back to the
monastery and oppose the days keep the
precepts in other words behave like
monks at least
occasionally because it's meritorious
and it can help your mind and who knows
maybe it will spur another decision to
become a monk again or something
uh today i don't think there is a i
think any monastery just go and stay in
any monastery and
you will have to keep their precepts and
kind of behave like monks so
yeah there are many there are other
monasteries retreat centers where you
can go and
um gonna be you have to be very
restrained uh follow the routine and so on so so
uh follow the routine and so on so so
that's about it
yeah you're just going to become an
anagarika into the monastery so you're
not a monk but you have to behave like a
monk like exactly back in in the west we had
like exactly back in in the west we had
to spend i mean you go to asia and i
think in thailand you don't even have to be in
in thailand you don't even have to be in
anagarika but in in europe we had to be
a whole year as a nagarika
then a whole year is a novice and only
then we get arupa sampada
so by that time you'll kind of know if
you if you really you know
you know what to expect and you know if
if you want to do it and if you can't do
it
so for two years yet and actually some
honesty is even longer for two to three
years before you can you can become a
monk yeah i have several questions but i will
yeah i have several questions but i will
try to put it
in one it's quite similar to
question before for a lay person
how it is which is the way to live
in this society which we i think can all
agree is based on wrong values uh
is based on wrong values uh
how can we maintain our inner peace
in other words for example in this
society you have to most of the time
you have to most of the time
you have to struggle to maintain your
ego to protect this ego
from bad influences bad people and so on
and this can be sometimes very stressful
so what is your suggestion
to keep inner peace or try to
you you know you can't have inner peace
in that setting as simple as that
household life is crowded and dusty
dirty full of people with ignorance so
it's you can't have inner peace there is
a reason
that every every suta starts like that
so if you truly want completing the
peace you have to live that life so if
you can't live their life you have to
recognize that you can only have a
partial inner peace
and that inner peace comes out of sense
out of self-control if you can develop
self-control and you can develop
self-control they will lay people in the
suttas that free themselves from sensuality and
that free themselves from sensuality and
ill will still in that setting
obviously they were not as busy as
occupied and as
engaged as somebody who is completely
uninterested in any development
so you do need to keep the precepts
protect your environment they would then
protect your precepts they would then
protect your sense restraint
and start developing self-control so
you're going to have to endure a lot of
things one way or the other as a monk
you have to endure a lot
but you want to stay there you have to
do it a lot as you know i said existence
is a full-time job
it's not just something peop like people
like to think they just go through
so if you want inner peace be clear with
yourself how much of that peace you want and how
how much of that peace you want and how
much you're willing to
compromise on it and then uh yeah
precepts five precepts ideally eight precepts and
five precepts ideally eight precepts and
uh start developing that
self-control through them and then you
will know exactly you know when to say
no to people and what's fine but it
isn't because you started developing
these criterias of your behavior
but probably the most important thing is
to realize it's going to be hard work
one way or the other it is unavoidable
so you want peace you have to work for
it the more you work for it the more
peace you have
and that's what's i think but you give
up little you get a little peace
you work to give up a lot you get a lot
of peace if you work and give
everything up internally well you get
all the peace
but it doesn't happen magically there's
no magical technique a recipe
a method they will then just do the work
for you
you can't be you can't have it both ways
so you can't be in the world
engage with the world and at the same
time expect to be
disengaged from the world and peaceful
it's either or so that's what i mean
it's a compromise
and you have to see how far you yourself
are willing to go
in that compromise because if you really
value the peace
you could already you know start
tailoring your life and minimizing
engagements it will be work but then it
will pay off later on you're going to
have less
less disturbances and so on if you can't
do that
well ask yourself why can't you do that
but what stops you
like what stops anyone from from leaving
the household life
honestly speaking at any given second
and sing like i say that to the monks
like don't don't use the tradition
and robes and the environment you live
in to keep your monk
make sure basically your mind prefers
this lifestyle so you go beyond any
chance of this robot on a kind of
sensuality or anything stupid
so every time you should ask yourself
say what
what what prevents me from just walking
away from whatever i'm doing right now
this very second
what sense of duty have i assumed
so you want to make sure you're clear
about it because that's how you will
start to value the right things
not just do them out of sense because
see you might actually not be changing
your environment sufficiently enough
out of some blindly assumed sense of
duty that you don't even really have
but you just fear to think about it so
you don't give it up
so now you feel stuck oh i want peace
but i can't give this up well
you can't have it both ways see which
one you want more and then grit your
teeth and you have to endure it
and then maybe like if you think
solution will present itself later
fine you have to be patient until then
but again you have to be honest with
yourself and see how much input you
yourself have in your own environment it's not
have in your own environment it's not
given
you can say no to everything
if there is a good reason to do so
uh how to cultivate mindfulness or
concentration to the extent
that you are aware of your thinking and
acting before you do it
and how to recognize habits thoughts
that harm us along the way
as i understand it we should avoid the
harmful that's great resistance and delusions
that's great resistance and delusions
both grit and resistance are
fairly easy to detect what about
delusions delusions practically are distractions
delusions practically are distractions
so stuff you do to distract yourself
through your senses
not necessarily sensual or necessarily
rooted in your will
so watching tv reading news um
talking to others if there is no point
that's often the buddha we talk a lot about
often the buddha we talk a lot about
avoiding idol chatter pointless chatter
and all
it's even incorporated in those
practical precepts
um so things you would do throughout the
day little activities and so on just to keep
little activities and so on just to keep
yourself busy all of that would be
cultivating delusion we we covered that
in that
biting and non-activity talk i think or
at least
part of it but the point is yeah that is
the hardest obviously to deal with
but you can certainly start doing
something about it on a small scale
so you know you're not central you're
not angry but
okay so why don't you just sit with
yourself doing nothing
why do you need to you know put around
on your phone or do some work project or
read something why is that necessary why
do you depend on the activity of a
neutral kind
so it's it's not as i said unwholesome
in terms of greed or real will
but you do depend on an external
activity that requires your senses so
it is it is distracting in that sense
and that's exactly why
delusion is the hardest to see and
hardest to uproot as the widow would say
so i also have a question so um
so we are all sort of on the way so we
all practice some
sensory strength and probably some
silver obviously
obviously we are not uh as
also as lay people but also probably
also as monastics
that develop that we can say that we
have accomplished already
for instance the previous steps on the
gradual training
practice in ghana yeah so does it mean
that in order to start what is in ghana
you need to well uh to
accomplish all the previous steps or is
it like this that you can start
sort of a little bit of practice of
janna even
if you are not completely sensory
strained and yeah
maybe uh didn't fulfill some other
steps completely uh no no you have to
you have to
have fully developed in virtue
because they were even in the suttas
where the some monks did have
janas and then they started sleeping in
their virtues and then they couldn't get
janus anymore although they knew exactly
how and what to do
but their actions undermine them so it's
absolutely not negotiable and that's by
the way vagina is
a full thorough complete withdrawal from
unwholesome on the basis of your behavior
on the basis of your behavior
that has been cultivated beforehand of
withdrawal from the unwholesome
through keeping the precepts abstaining
from sexuality
ill will pretty much all these things
are rooted in greed and ill will
and that is already the practice of
samadhi by the way that's why sila
samadhi and then panya it's not sila and now let
and then panya it's not sila and now let
me go and find what samadhi is
perfecting your sela is a way of
composing yourself rightly
away from the unwholesome states so you
don't have to think like you're not
practicing jhana
simply by keeping precepts you are
actually you are you are closer to jhana
by keeping the precepts
than if you are doing you run upon a
sati without the precepts
it's withdrawing your mind from the um
unwholesome in the world on account of
which the pleasure from that withdrawal arises
the pleasure from that withdrawal arises
in the first genre when the mind
recognizes i am safe here
and the the very first part of that
withdrawal is the the sila and virtue
not a meditation technique or or
something you read you should do in
order to get the jhana
yeah i understand this but um
and nevertheless should one still
practice or you shouldn't just
completely give it up
and i don't know just do do nothing as
you suggested in one of your talks right
right well it depends on your motivation
if you're doing anapanasati because you
can't sit still
you're not doing the right unapologetic
you're just trying trying to find
something to occupy yourself with
you're being mindless about your own
experience not self-aware
and many people would be doing
meditation for that reason because if
they just sit
away they start to lose their mind
so meditation becomes something to keep
you occupied while you're seemingly
doing nothing but you're actually doing
a lot
and that's not anapanasati anapanasati
as dhyanapanasati sutra says
well it first requires the right view
uh so you need to have been very
accomplished in virtue and understanding
of the dharma beforehand
and then secondly it culminates in
fulfillment of the four foundations of
mindfulness there is no mention of anapanasati boom
there is no mention of anapanasati boom
experience of jhana
in the actual suit of anapanasata the
buddha was teaching
so that i'm not i'm not trying to debate
now what leads to jhana or whatever but
that should be enough to just make you
question your own view of what jhana is
i don't think we can get into that now
but if you if you look into the suttas
you might see that it might be slightly
different from what you're expecting it
to be
and the same reason like why do you want
to practice jhana again ask yourself
uh while you know that maybe you haven't
been really fulfilled in all the
prerequisites why do you ask can i still why do you
why do you ask can i still why do you
want jhana
without having developed virtue and
everything else what do you expect that
jhana to give to you
do you think it will bypass the fact
that you haven't developed the virtue
do you think it will just give you the
pleasure that it's nice so you just want
a bit of pleasure before you go back to
work well that is sensuality 101
let me go let me get some pleasure so i
can then go back to work so that i can
get more pleasure
and that's not ghana then
so just be clear about your motivation
and while you're clarifying your
motivation why you want jhana why you
want meditation and so on
what is what is it supposed to
accomplish for me
be clear about all those things why are
you're clarifying those things
keep practicing virtue and fulfilling
those prerequisites that you know
you should be fulfilling
yeah i can have a question that is
somewhat related to what we were just
talking about
i would be very grateful if you could
perhaps spend some time talking about the role
spend some time talking about the role
of
reflection and understanding in
cultivating the right mindfulness i
think this ties in nicely with what
we've just
been talking about namely this there's
this idea of
um that is
very present and prominent in
contemporary circles
whereby the idea is to cultivate
mindfulness by merely observing
um merely being aware
so developing a pure awareness that uh
is
devoid of all thought and understanding
and then
the implicit idea is that you are
somehow going to enter
into a unique frame or state of mind
that will
somehow absolve you of
all the things that plague you basically
i mean i'm oversimplifying here
intentionally but i would say that the
implicit premise behind many of the of the
premise behind many of the of the
contemporary approaches is precisely
this and when everyone reads sutas
and when everyone reads sutas
one sees that verbs such as
understanding and thinking and whatnot are present
and thinking and whatnot are present
they are
they are an integral part of the path
but it's also clear that this understanding
it's also clear that this understanding
this thinking this knowledge is not
say a factual propositional knowledge
that is
often taught in say epistemological
courses so i would be very grateful if you could
so i would be very grateful if you could
talk
a little bit about the reflection
the role of reflection and understanding
in
the contemplative path maybe with
concrete examples
so that it is more clear as to how one
might integrate it as um as uh
integrate it as um as uh
efficiently as possible into one's
practice uh well before i answer that we do have
uh well before i answer that we do have
that whole
playlist on our youtube channel about
meditation and a lot of those talks
address exactly that you know the kind
of contemporary notions of focusing
practices and so on where people try to
avoid thinking in the problem expecting it
thinking in the problem expecting it
will magically disappear
and then the idea of samadhi and janna
become extension of that just i'm
focused hard enough from one pointedness
and then i have this special experience
where i'm unaware of myself and
everything has disappeared and was so
blissful so not just that that's not mindfulness
so not just that that's not mindfulness
that's completely the opposite direction
that well that's literally absence of
your mind
how can absence of your mind be fullness
of your mind mindful
it's it's just the opposite direction
reflection as the role of reflection
as the role of reflection
in the practice of the path as you said
it's from the beginning till the end
that's pretty much the unifying factor
it is because of your reflection that
you recognize the
nature of your situation as a lay person
it is because of your reflection that
you recognize that there is an option to
you know
leave that become a monk or at least get
the precepts on
so it is because of your reflection that
you adopt the moral set of behavior in
the virtue and you start valuing it
it is because of your reflection that
you then grow out of your precepts
your mind experience calmness and
composure and account of those priestess
that's your samadhi
and when that has developed it is
because of your reflection you get to
understand the complete clarity
pretty much of things that need to be
understand for the freedom
so that's why i would have said you
cannot have too much of mindfulness
you cannot have too much of that
reflection so sure sometimes you can be more
so sure sometimes you can be more
actively thinking about things
and then sometimes you need to come down
a bit and just drop the subject and calm
down and so on
that's kind of the difference between
vipassana and some other practice
but fundamentally all is within
mindfulness
and the role is is uh well
immeasurable and and often even like
again when the
when lay people will be talking to the
buddha not even to the monks he would he
would all he would do is encourage them
to start you know questioning like don't
go by the tradition don't go by the you
know seniority or something ask yourself wait
seniority or something ask yourself wait
why do i value this why do i hold this
why do i do this what do i want from my
life and so on and the same and that thing
and so on and the same and that thing
never changes
you know and then for a monk who has
left that life and lives that he should
keep constantly hmm is there no reason
constantly hmm is there no reason
central lust in me
is there an original will in me can
anonymous centralized arise in me
no he doesn't ask that there's some sort
of you know pointless abstract questions
of mantras that he repeats throughout
the day mumbles to himself no he really
needs to know wait can non-arisen
unwholesome states arise in me
i don't know well there you go that's
your work you need to know
because not knowing means yes they can
you're not clear about it that's how
those things arise so then he diligently
sets on to do the work and purifies his
state mind states you know first watch of the
mind states you know first watch of the
night third watch of the night and so on
that's what purification is it's not
focusing on the nostril and becoming
mindless completely unaware of
everything around you
it's reviewing your mind not allowing
anything unwholesome to be welcomed
delighted in accepted not acting out of
anything wholesome and then contemplating your
wholesome and then contemplating your
way out of it
through that sense restraint and uh and
not acting out
and none of that is possible to do if
you're not mindful and reflexive
can i have something i would just like
to eat yeah
something i have a
subsequent question that's related to
this [Music]
[Music]
why would you say thoughts and thinking
in general
nowadays has become so demonized
to the point where buddhism for many
people is basically
identified with non-thinking so this
ideal or this idea of
thinking being the the the
the main culprit of all the
existential problems how is this
is this maybe you know a symptom of
the western mind dealing with its own
problems and then just projecting them
onto onto buddhism or why would
why would the thought be so
vilified well i don't know specifically
the western mind but basically it's a
symptom of a mind or a symptom of a culture
of a mind or a symptom of a culture
that has proliferated significantly into
sensuality so the expectation for quick fix and
so the expectation for quick fix and
blaming the external things for problems
it's the automatic default behavior
and then when sometimes people cannot
blame the obvious external things for
the problems well the next external
thing is my thinking in regard to the problem
is my thinking in regard to the problem
so then they turn to spirituality
hopefully and spirituality does offer that because
and spirituality does offer that because
you know most of those people believe in
the same solutions as in
stop thinking and the problem will
disappear as like well thinking was
never the problem
and that's the whole point but for as
long as you think
ironically enough that your thinking is
the problem well you you're
contradicting yourself
because you can't stop thinking because
trying to stop thinking is your own
thought so all you're hoping is basically
so all you're hoping is basically
hopefully sufficiently enough i can
ignore this problem and then it will go
away and that's what people so that's when
and that's what people so that's when
they expect a quick fix and the quickest
fix is
block your thoughts from recognizing the
problem not
hey my thoughts reveal that problem is
there let me then deal with the problem then
let me then deal with the problem then
regardless of what i think there will be
no problem there
that's too much work now so it's it's
sensuality it's
essential behavior and i don't mean like
crazy indulgent or something just people
depend on their senses
things that come through the senses uh
activities distractions
and which means every time you engage in
that direction you are
losing basis for developing patients
basis for developing endurance and basis
for developing self-reflection
because this is pleasant and covers any
problem up
so why do i need to bother to dig up a
wound and feel the pain of it
but i can just paste this magical cream
and feel nothing and continue with my
life well until you can't and then it's too
well until you can't and then it's too
late to do anything about it
the wound has festered and spread around
and now you're done
but again the sensuality will prevent
you to see that that's why people don't
see the peril in it
so yeah blaming thoughts and that's why
exactly as i said meditation
practices that are about focusing and
not thinking are exactly that
extension of sensuality like an animal
trying to hunt a prey that it really
values and it will provide me with
satisfaction so people are trying to hunt the special
so people are trying to hunt the special
experience
they will now provide me with great
pleasure and all the disappearances of
my problems
that's it that's what people tried
that's why but most people turn to
religion for
and it's fine if you turn to the
religion for those mistaken reasons but
it's not fine if you never actually
start questioning those and hopefully
you know upgrade your expectations and
practice like sensual mind cannot expect
like sensual mind cannot expect
enlightenment to be anything other than
great sensuality and that's fine but
it's when you start to do it and learn
about it
if you never abandoned those sexual
expectations well then you're just well
you're not getting anywhere
yeah you were just talking about the
reflection and contemplation
practices so how to get to the root
of the problem how to um so
i was just thinking about this so you
recognize the prop that you have a
problem right
and would you say that the correct way
of contemplating and meditating upon
um that problem of
why a certain thing causes desire
aversion etc
it's not the why but the breaking it
down into the constituent
parts into the five candas for example
no no no that would be basically pretty
much an abstract analysis you're doing
in order to get rid of the problem
so if you see if you want to if you see
a problem with five counters and so on
you want to see that from the problem
you don't want to be putting it into a
problem and making it be so
that's what often people oh i reflect
this and everything is in each and
each comes i look at this all that is
just trying to manage
this problem that you can't deal with
using buddhist terminology and so on
you want to recognize that whatever
problem is there first of all it doesn't
matter why
it doesn't matter how it doesn't matter
who that's like
the the similarly the buddha gave in the
suttas like a man gets shot with an
arrow and he's bleeding and it's very painful
and he's bleeding and it's very painful
but he refuses to deal with bleeding and
the pain
until he finds out who shot him why they
shot him
what clan was the person that shot him
could have he done something to to not
be
all of that is he waste his time and he
bleeds to death
he tries to manage his suffering provide
the satisfying answers to justified
suffering all in order to not deal with the
all in order to not deal with the
suffering so that's the first step to
recognize is that
doesn't matter why what what for and who
matters is that sooner or later
something will bother you something will
arise for you
and that's the problem doesn't matter
where he came from or for what reason
so then you start and that's already the
first step to stop
blaming the world or trying to justify
or psychologize
oh this is what happened so next time i
won't do that all of that is to try to
prevent your liability to suffer
the only way you can prevent that is by
becoming fully enlightened person
so you realize it's not about management
it's not about finding the underlying
causes or the reasons
it's about accepting the liability to
suffering feeling the suffering here and now
feeling the suffering here and now
whenever he wants to rise
not trying to prolong it but not trying
to get rid of it either
enduring it not breaking the precepts on
account of it
not distracting yourself with sensuality
on account of it and that will already
force your mind to see it
for what it is or at least stop turning
a blind eye to it
and from there you will get to if if you
endure that
that pure dukkha without a cover-up
without psychologizing without all these
distractions in regard to the dukkha
well everything else you read in the
suttas we're gonna start to make more
sense because now you actually have a basis
because now you actually have a basis
for the things that the buddha was
talking about and that's how your
your contemplation endowments on from
that abstract level of you know this is
one aggregate two aggregates three
aggregates comes down onto the very concrete level
comes down onto the very concrete level
of you see it
in what you're enduring not at the
expense of and not in regard to get rid
of what bothers you
and then incidentally enough they will
get rid of all the suffering
full understanding but not through the
management but through what we say
uprooting in our talks and that's the big
in our talks and that's the big
difference
so you might your mind might start
picking up stuff that you read from the
suttas but make sure you're not motivated by
but make sure you're not motivated by
trying to get rid of the suffering
you're not trying to understand it
you're trying to get rid of it with
justifications using the information you collected from
using the information you collected from
the suttas
and many people do that like oh yeah
yeah everything is a nietzsche yeah i
understand that especially when things
bother them they keep repeating the
mantra everything is in each everything is a
everything is in each everything is a
nature not because they understood on
each other
or they see directly it's just the
mantra helps them
dismiss the pain and
that's not the nature of what was
teaching about you first need to endure
things in order to see there on each
other not apply and paste like your response
not apply and paste like your response
over them
i think you said i think you said what i
was trying to say actually
it's not no i didn't mean the uh
abstract breaking it
down but feeling the feeling well sure
like again uh maybe i used abstract in
in in too
uh concise way but the point is if
you're trying
to even contemplate these aggregates and
everything else that you read from the
suitors in order to deal with the pain means you
in order to deal with the pain means you
want to get rid of your pain you're
acting out of a version towards pain and
that's why you will not see the dhamma
not because you haven't read the right
sutta it's because you still cultivate
the basic principle of craving
that the dharma begins with aversion to
its pain
lusting after pleasure and ignoring the
neutral feeling
so you will inevitably have to start
like that but if you keep you that's
what i mean if you keep your mind on
motivation why am i doing this
it can become apparent to you that you
are trying to contemplate the dharma
because you are still cultivating
aversion towards pain
and that's why you cannot get to the
dhamma because of that aversion
not because of your insufficient
cultivation or contemplation
so suffering needs to be accepted that's
what would have said
i teach only two things suffering and
freedom from it
so most people cannot even suffer
because they immediately go into the
mode of
aversion so whatever they do even
practice become monks or whatever
is to get rid of the suffering through
aversion so as a ultimate goal you sure you want
so as a ultimate goal you sure you want
to be free from suffering
that's fine but how you go about it will
determine whether you succeed or not
is your practice of getting rid still
rooted in aversion towards that
suffering or are you realizing okay i want to get
or are you realizing okay i want to get
ready which means
now i have to endure suffering for what
it is
not try to remove it on my own terms
and that's how you will basically stop
acting out of aversion
towards suffering can you please um
clarify what you mean on your own terms
yeah well that that's what it is see
like uh there is there is suffering
present for example something bothers
you you already by default refuse to accept
you already by default refuse to accept
it
even if you accept this suffering
emotionally you are reversed towards it
as the suitors would say there is a
version they're enduring
so whatever you do now it's rooted in
you acting out of that aversion which
means whatever you do
will be basically things you want to do
in order to remove this which is your
reverse but you're not removing your
aversion so that's like you try to do it on your
so that's like you try to do it on your
own terms as opposed to
realizing that you must accept the
suffering not try to do anything rooted
in a version
not try to do anything rooted in in your
own terms and then endure it
see enduring it is not on your own terms
because you don't want to do it you
reverse to it
and if you endure it sufficiently
without breaking the precepts or acting
out of it that's what i mean
stuff you read from the sutras you start
seeing it that you start recognizing it
in it
you don't need to be applying it and
thinking it actively
he's like oh as the suitors would say it
would become apparent
oh look it's there the only reason i
wasn't seeing it because i was too busy
acting out of a version
to see it so that's the difference
between doing it on your own terms or enduring
doing it on your own terms or enduring
it first which will prevent you to act
out on your own terms
also question from okay
so i am um reflected now a little bit
on your uh on your answer to my question
about samadhi
and jana um so
uh well i mean um i
what if uh for an individual the
well the inability to experience that
peace that one probably experiences
at retreats uh leads
leads him to abandon their lay life and
become a monastic
so is it is it so it seems to me
that this experience of of samadhi even
if it is
connected with sensuality can be
beneficial for for the progress so how do you view
for for the progress so how do you view
it
well becoming a monk is not a progress
in itself
so if you have a wrong view it won't
change even if you wear robes doesn't matter
even if you wear robes doesn't matter
so progress is if you experience the
right peace
progress is if you're clear from the
wrong views but this desire
to for peace yeah so so to see the
problem the problem with that is desire
for peace is fine
and it's fine if you're going to retreat
and get the best piece you can
but what is not fun is to think well
this piece stands in place of the right
piece because then you will not seek what the
because then you will not seek what the
right piece is
so that's my entire point here you you
should keep trying to get the peace
nobody says you shouldn't but what you
must be very careful is when you do so
you might fall into a view that the
relative peace you find
since that's the only piece you know
will be conflated with the peace that
the buddha was teaching and that's not
the case because otherwise you would be
at least the sotapanna anagami or an
arahant and that's always my point when i say oh
and that's always my point when i say oh
but the meditation techniques help me
well are you confusing that help
for the like fulfillment of the dharma
or are you fully aware
that that help is just managing until i
find a way how to pull the arrow out but
i never forget
that it's pulling off the arrow out that
my goal is
and people often do forget that if you
manage your uh
your pain if you find that temporary
piece long enough you will start
believing in it
so don't let that happen to you like now
you might be aware
but if you do start making the effort or
rather the more effort you make towards
management the more risk there is you're gonna
the more risk there is you're gonna
start believing that is what the
practice is and because of that
you won't start pushing further to find
where the actual practice is
and that's what happens when people go
to retreats and have super special
peaceful experiences they're just too
pleasing to be given up now
and somebody comes and tells them no no
that's not the peace the piece of
understanding is completely different
well they'll get upset with that person
because of the pleasure of the peace not
because they fully understood what that
piece was
and they know this person is wrong no
it's simply threat to the pleasure that
they know
that's it that's all it takes for you to
fall into the wrong view
if you're careful if you're transparent
about it fine no problem
keep trying at any piece you can get
just don't lose perspective that peace
begins only with sauda party or higher
not with a special experience of your
meditation
yeah okay that's what exactly what what
my point was and also what my
understanding is yeah thank you
and then so if possible i have another
question um so yeah so we are discussing now very
um so yeah so we are discussing now very
practical things and
yeah and this is yeah this is very
helpful for me
but um so but there are some things in
buddhism which i have a really problem
with like um for instance like belief in
like um for instance like belief in
rebirths
and and things like this and maybe some
talks about cosmology that
woulda gave so uh what is their attitude
towards them for somebody who doesn't
have uh
this experience don't conflate the two
you might have a problem with those side
things and who knows
where those conversations were rooted in
and and what those things meant you know
like in the certain says 500 arahants
came and so on
it's just 500 meant it was like a like a
a common common way of saying many i'm
not i'm not saying that oh it would have
i'm not saying that oh it would have
didn't mean the
like future lives and previous lives and
gods i'm just saying it's never directly
i'm just saying it's never directly
related to to for noble truths and
freedom from suffering
and that should really be your concern
because if your problem with cosmology
prevents you from actually that which
you can verify for yourself which is
craving and freedom from suffering in
this life well you'll be at great loss
so take that as something that maybe you
can think about later
don't look for faults on account of
which you will avoid doing things you
are capable
of and you would benefit immensely from
but yeah you don't need to accept it by
the way or you must believe no you don't
it's never directly related to any
relevant suit of freedom from suffering
or anything else
so you realize yeah it's not really
directly related and i'm sure there were
plenty of people in india at the time
they didn't believe in rebirth they had
all sorts of teachers they said no this
is the only life and so on
and uh and it was not a requirement
because why because you suffer in this
life you're pressured by your emotions
in this life
you don't escape from fear and anxiety
in this life that's all you need to know
and you know accepting buddhist
cosmology does not make you more
of a buddhist than if you don't accept
it what makes you more of a buddhist is
if you keep the five precepts the eight
precepts and apply basically your tireless energy
and apply basically your tireless energy
day and night
to to cultivate the buddha's instruction
that's it that's what makes you buddhist
not your proclamation or belief in you
know gods and so on
that the buddha laid out in those sutas
and if it bothers you well don't let
that become a motivation for avoiding
things that you can practice in this
life that you can understand for
yourself in this life
so endure that bother in other words
that's what i'm saying
endurance is pretty much the the the
crossroads people come at
between either you're going to manage
try to manage and get rid of your
suffering or you're actually going the right way
or you're actually going the right way
of being able to approach it eventually
and get the right view and so on
it's not blind endurance it's not
focused on your nostrils and endure
it's mindful full self-awareness not
acting out of greed
aversion or distraction endurance the
foremost austerity that
it talks about so it is it's it's like
the basis
the basis for the right practice for the
direction of the right practice
being able to do things without acting
out
and you probably hear or read me often
saying that
not act out not act out
rooted in emotions against which you
have either aversion
or lust or you want to distract yourself
from that's why sealing sensory strain
needs to come first
as a container because doesn't matter
how much mentally you wish to not act
out if your body is still cat is pretty much
if your body is still cat is pretty much
the habit of acting out you're acting
out he's just wishful thinking to to believe
he's just wishful thinking to to believe
you know
okay so sebastian has a question i have
a question about anxiety
um we've touched upon this briefly i
would like to
um kind of bring forth this
what seems to be like a dual aspect of
anxiety now on the one hand of course it seems
now on the one hand of course it seems
to be
an unwholesome mental state
but on the other hand there's something
to be said
for a potentially beneficial
impact and aspect of anxiety
after all it was existential anxiety
that led buddha only
on his part it is and since
it is existential anxiety that buddha
speaks of when he says that monks
everything is burning
it is existential anxiety that you said
yourself is sometimes lacking even in among the
is sometimes lacking even in among the
monastics
so how does one cultivate this
existential anxiety existential dread
this ongoing awareness
of let's say mortality in the broadest
sense of the
term with anxiety basically the problem
with anxiety is that people want to get
rid of it because it's unpleasant
in itself anxiety is not unwholesome
anxiety is just
basically revealing that there is
something that that that can still
undermine you
that you can still suffer on account of
so anxiety is a mental state
well people like to think it's
unwholesome because you justify them
trying to get rid of it by any means
necessary you know including medications
and so on
it's not it's just a recognition of uh
emotional recognition of a symptom of
of a problem that's anxiety pretty much
a sense of urgency that the buddha would
inspire in monks
the ones they got negligent so
and that's pretty much what what you
need to do first don't try to get rid of
it
don't try to find the answers for it but
surprise endure it
if you'd if if you wonder how to say
like you
you can't find your anxiety anymore or
it's not coming up
it's either it's only for two reasons
either you became an arahant or you
became complacent
if you're in arahant no problem you got
your answer if you are complacent
all you need to do and the anxiety will
come back in no time
is tighten your sense restraint
and you'll see it will be there fear of
death will be there just by saying who
to sensuality the first thing that comes
knocking is fear of death and fear of dying and
is fear of death and fear of dying and
and dying your loved ones or whatever
else and that's why people immediately
run back they feel justified
but so whether it's a monk or a lay
person if you don't have anxiety it
means you don't have enough sense
restraint and just think about it i mean take a
and just think about it i mean take a
average layman
and tell him how about your you you
abstain from sexual intercourse for the
rest of your life
as a demand
if it were to be taken seriously every
single person would freak out at that
thought it would be this intense arising of pain
it would be this intense arising of pain
and fear and the thought of never
experiencing that central pleasure ever
again and within no time they'll be full of
and within no time they'll be full of
anxiety and and the minds will be just
swinging with the moods left and right
so and same for the monks if there is no
anxiety if there is no sense of urgency
means ah you are you're getting
complacent in your environment in your
setups or whatever else so you all you
need to do is just start
saying no to your eyes ears nose mouth
touches and so on avoid the comfort and
so on and anxiety will be back fear of
death will be back because it just
reveals the situation you're still in
you are not free from death
but if you want to practice with anxiety
and cultivate it
the basis of virtue is necessary
so it's like an indicator of um a
progression in training yeah it's it's
not anxiety is not an indicator it's how
much you resist it or not that's the
indicator of your progression
so if you're not resisting it not trying
to justify it get rid of it
and it's still there then yeah then it's
a good indicator
that you're doing things rightly but
yeah how much anxiety you feel that
doesn't matter the same reason that that
um that people suffer so much and have
fears in in the in the first reply
is because sensuality is the only means
of escape
people know but it's the escape that
makes the problem even worse so it's not
really an escape
so you don't try to not have anxiety you
will most certainly if you stop
practicing sense restraint and keeping
sealer and and so on and then during
solitude the point is ah to train my mind to not
the point is ah to train my mind to not
resist it with aversion as something i
must get rid of and then it will cease
to be unpleasant
it's only unpleasant pretty much
anything that any suffering it's
suffering because you are reversed
towards it not because it's unpleasant
in itself that's the truth of the first
novel truth
your craving is the root of every
suffering even in those extreme
circumstances where i don't know highway robbers
where i don't know highway robbers
attack a monkey and started hacking him
with machetes and so on
the buddha said if he has any resistance
towards that emotionally
he's not he hasn't fulfilled my teaching
because that's never where the suffering
is rooted the extreme discomfort
is not the root of dukkha it's your
aversion towards it every single time no
exception so anxiety is a problem because people
so anxiety is a problem because people
are reversed towards it
not because it's a problem in itself
well fear is a problem it's because
people are reversed towards it not
because the problem in itself
fear may be just telling you oh this is
a dangerous situation for my body for my
health or for something
but it's you being a verse emotionally
towards it that's why you suffer an
account of all of those mental states
so i i i have to say that
i i didn't realize that the necessary
connection between uh increasing sense
restraint and increa increasing anxiety so
and increa increasing anxiety so
um like um i know
let's say if you adopt another another
serial or an additional c does it
to let's say if you um
already attend to five or eight um
then i know you either either
see that you can do it or you see that
you cannot do it
and and um how do you mean that that uh
adding some additional seals is going to
to increase your anxiety
so as i said you will not be
experiencing anxiety
if you're either fully free from
sensuality and almost in other hands say
uh or because you're still using means
of escape
through sensuality so that's why
sensuality that's what i mean it's not
sensuality is not so intoxicating for
people just because it's pleasant it's
because it's the only form of
like approximation of an escape that
they would know from the unpleasantness
of existence in itself
so that's what as i said even when
people don't necessarily
uh engage with course sensuality or real
will just having things to do needing things
just having things to do needing things
to do depending on activity of the
senses is still your means of escape so start
is still your means of escape so start
restraining that
and you will feel anxious because you
are refusing to engage with the only
direction of escaping the unpleasant
pressure or pressure of unresolved existence of
or pressure of unresolved existence of
your of
of yourself because if you resolved it
you would be another hand and there
would be no pressure for you
so that's what i mean by sense restraint
like precepts sure that's fine but
now ask yourself okay i'm doing i'm
reading this book
am i self aware while i'm doing that
well not really well then i'll stop
reading it
i'll just send your solitude and boredom
and see where that takes me well it will
take you straight to anxiety every
single time
unless you have uprooted it that's why
people are terrified of boredom having
nothing to do
and that's that's pretty much like say
if you were to put another hunt in a
cell without anything he would not lose
his mind because there is no mind to be
lost in that sense
he has dealt with it beforehand so
there's nothing for him to lose there
there's nothing for him to resist there
if you if you lock him in a little box
he will not suffer he will not
experience terror and anxiety because
basically he's already abandoned this
life
so that's what i mean by increasing
sealant i mean like add some random
observances or precepts
mechanically as a sense of duty no i
mean find then other things you do within
find then other things you do within
your good seal and virtue
and see why you're doing them and
restrain them wind yourself up a bit
more and you're going to feel anxiety
if you need to like don't do it if
you're already full of anxiety
like you can have too much of a sense of
urgency as everybody would say so only
when you get
oh am i actually you know am i feeling
the urgency of practice i'm not sure
well maybe i should restrain myself
maybe today i will not see talk to anyone i
today i will not see talk to anyone i
will not leave this room i will not
switch tv or phone on i will just sit
alone with myself which is neutral in itself
with myself which is neutral in itself
by the way there's nothing bad just
sitting with yourself in the room with
your own thoughts
yet nobody can do it well unless people
who develop samadhi
and then become other hunts and so on so
you realize okay that's a challenge and
if you go in that direction
as i said anxiety is guaranteed boredom
leads to anxiety anxiety leads to dread
so you recognize that you cannot deal
with it overnight
but you certainly don't adopt a view
that it should not be dealt with or you
can avoid dealing with it
because that's where radha chip is
once the arjun chad die before you die
so abandon this life before it abandons
you
and you abandon it by completely
removing any desire towards it
any lust any aversion and so on any
unwholesome mental state
uh i have one more written
question from raymond um
maybe you already answered to that
question but i really maybe have
something to add
uh how buddhism understands self or ego
so it's really this identity self the
biggest enemy
and then how to treat or limit it again
when people talk abstractly about it
um it misses the point that's when they
ask the buddha so master gautama says
there is no self and he wouldn't answer
it
because it's already wrong assumption
practically speaking how you want to go
about it is self
identity ego whatever you want to call
it it's a symptom of a problem
it's not a problem in itself
so how do you deal with the symptom of a
problem well you recognize what it is
the symptom of
and the suit is tell us it's a symptom
of greed aversion delusion
it's a symptom of not understanding the
nature of existence it's a symptom of
ownership owning things possessions acquisitions
owning things possessions acquisitions
as they would have talked about
that you acquired through sensuality and
pursuit of pleasure that you get through
those acquisitions
that's why you have a functioning sense
of self there that endures and becomes
the owner the
the appropriator the controller the
master and so on
so how do you curb it well sense
restraint start saying no to your
desires uh relinquish unnecessary uh
uh relinquish unnecessary uh
acquisitions don't seek to gain more
contemplate death contemplate um losing
death contemplate um losing
things that are dear to you and you are
curbing your sense of self and it's
going to feel like dying
because yeah that self is dying your
identity is ceasing
and that's literally going to feel like
death because that's what death is
cessation of identity
that's why arahant cannot die because he
has already killed his identity in that
sense so death doesn't apply to him and even
so death doesn't apply to him and even
when the suitors talk about it
they say such and such person dies such
and such person dies but when arahant
dies they doesn't use the word die it
says aggregates break apart because death
aggregates break apart because death
doesn't apply to him
death applies when there is still
lingering identity
so if i understand you my name is
raymond if i understand your level so if i
if i understand your level so if i
accept
that like a normal state of my life
then i will be afraid of any delusions
and you can't accept it as a matter of
choice though
because as i said the underlying problem
of you not the reason why you don't
accept death while you refuse where you
fear death that's it that's already a
form of non-acceptance is because
you're not free from sensual desires
you're not free from aversion you're not
free from ignoring your own self
distracting yourself from yourself the
reason why you don't accept death is not
because you decided to not accept it
so you can decide to accept it but
unless you uproot
the underlying tendencies of lust
aversion distraction
that feed the actual non-acceptance of
it you will not be free from it
so it's good to accept death but make
sure you don't fall into a trap
of like that psychologization as i say
whereby yes
i accept death i'm at peace with it and
then continue with your desires and
aversions that's actually if you look closely
that's actually if you look closely
contradiction in terms there's just on
the level of belief
you believe that you accepted death but
you'll be surprised when the actual
death comes you realize how little that
acceptance will matter
it only mattered while you were alive
believing that you accepted it
so you don't need to decide to accept
death or to decide to not accept death
if you start diminishing your desires uh
practice sense restraint
and endure not acting out of craving
towards your feelings
you are actually freeing yourself from
death however
you know small steps those might be you
are still going in that direction
that's where some people in the suttas
when they never encountered the buddha
but they were
practicing on their own and obviously
were doing it more or less rightly
when they came across the buddha one
sentence made him an arahant
fully enlightened just hearing one
instruction from the buddha because they
actually did all that work of removing
the underlying tendencies because of
which they were not enlightened then the
they were not enlightened then the
buddha just set the pieces right the
pieces that they built and cultivated
correctly so so you can't just accept it without
so so you can't just accept it without
having had that basis
developed and cultivated thoroughly and
sufficiently
thank you very good answer can i put
another question
for them i am 52 years old and all my
life i
had built a house of cart
so it's very hard to me
to destroy this house of cards
and started a new life
yeah so there's been like it's you will
obviously have
you know fear of death recognition that
it's it's coming closer
but don't you you can't think about it
or not it's up to you but recognize that
dealing with that problem with that
actual fear
is in controlling your other behavior
towards life
it's not like how will i address with
this now so that's what women
practice before it's too late because
now you still can doesn't matter if
you're 53 or 63 you still have
functioning senses
you your faculties of making choices
and being transparent in regard to your
motivation about those
are still there so use that
to start diminishing uh lust
acting out of lust acting out of craving
acting out of a version
and doing it on that emotional level and
not giving in
keeping the precepts pretty much what
the buddha advised that king when he
said what would you do if if there is a man
what would you do if if there is a man
from the east west north or south four
men come and tell you
there are four great mountains coming
your way and those mountains
are crushing everything in the way there
is no escape
every direction you try to run you just
run towards one of the mountains
and he said well what is there to do
lord i would then be restrained practice
dharma make merit
keep the virtue you know that's pretty
much the only life thing to do because
you can't outrun it
and he says well so i'm telling you
there are four mountains crushing you
it's holding
old age and death coming your way so you
better do what you just said you would
do in that instance
so that's what i mean whether you think
about the mountains and death and how
close you are
the way to deal with it is to start
being mindful
sense restraint on the level of your
day-to-day behavior and choices you make
in between those reflections
i have one question regarding monastic
discipline so um as far as we know some rules
so um as far as we know some rules
in in party mocha were caused just by
well just by the opinions uh how things
should be at the times of the buddha
where it's just like not not cutting
trees and things like this so why why is it
and things like this so why why is it
important
nowadays to to attend to these rules and
still keep them well that was the uh it
was actually that happened right after
the buddha died
uh ananda said that uh
oh the lord said we can abandon all
these minor rules
and then the other hand said the council
said well which one were the minor rules
according to the lord
and whenever others said well i forgot
to ask that
so they could have speculated and had a
pretty good guess what the minor rule
was but then they said well
if we do that the first thing people
will say look their head teacher died
and the first thing they do
is start reducing the amount of rules so
let's keep all of them since it makes no
difference like the rules that you have to keep
like the rules that you have to keep
that have nothing to do with the dhamma
are not in the way of your practicing
the dharma
and and uh if uh like um
if there are many of those rules as well
were often like had
uh were qualified in themselves like oh
this is an offense unless
it's done for this reason or in case of
this you can do this but if that's not the
you can do this but if that's not the
case you can't do that
so in other words they're quite flexible
in themselves so there isn't really any
of those rules that would be in the way
of you practicing correctly
and that's the reason why it's kept just
because another forgot to ask
and it would have looked bad upon the
order and upon the value of dhamma for
those who haven't understood it but
might have had chance to understand it
they say look
i don't want to listen to them the
teacher died and they were already
disrespecting him
so it was for benefit of others they
still adhere to the rules and we do so
any more questions
second time
third time thank you very much for your
time and for very good answers
well have a nice day then okay
take care likewise